<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A prognostication for the yere of Christ Jesus our Lord &amp; Sauiour, 1566 wherein are declared dyuers notable thinges, as you shal perceaue by the readyng therof : whiche (if God so permit) ar like to come to passe ... / set forth by John Securis ...</title>
            <author>Securis, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1566</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18569</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 510.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1477</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20186030</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20186030</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23740</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18569)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23740)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1700:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A prognostication for the yere of Christ Jesus our Lord &amp; Sauiour, 1566 wherein are declared dyuers notable thinges, as you shal perceaue by the readyng therof : whiche (if God so permit) ar like to come to passe ... / set forth by John Securis ...</title>
                  <author>Securis, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Thomas Marsh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1566.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸.</note>
                  <note>"Formerly STC 22147"--STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: contains Prognostication only (signatures A1-A8).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Almanacs, English.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23740:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtication for the yere of Chriſt Ieſus our lord &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. <hi>1566.</hi> Wherin are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared dyuers notable thinges, as you ſhal perceaue by the rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng therof: whiche (if God ſo permit) at like to come to paſſe as wel in this our Climate; as alſo in certain other co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treis. Set forth by <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Securis,</hi> Phiſition in Saliſbury.</p>
            <p>Anno Domini. 1566.</p>
            <p>Anno Mundi. 5528.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Thomas Marſh.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="astrological_forecast">
            <pb facs="tcp:23740:2"/>
            <div n="12 March-13 September" type="astronomical_half-year">
               <head>¶ Of the firſt part or reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of this yere, <hi>1566.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning the one half of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aſtronomical yere, being the .xi. day of Marche at noone, &amp; ſo ending the .xiii. of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bout .viii. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock after noon.</head>
               <p>AFter that I had well vie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face of the heauens, at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Sunne into the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall vernal point (whiche is the firſt ſcruple or minute of Aries) I founde the wytty, ſubtil <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>e planet Mercury, to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> well of the aſcendent <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he firſt reuolution. Of the whiche reuolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. the Sunne as a mighty lorde and kyng, chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ſome part with him. I fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:23740:2"/>alſo, that ſtoute ſturdy furious Mars, to occupy, yea rather by violence to withhold the chiefeſt part of all the horoſcope<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is the Eaſt angle, being the firſt in order of all the .xii. houſes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomicall figure, which houſe alſo concerneth mans lyfe, from his birth vnto his liues ende.</p>
               <p>I founde alſo Iupiter, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and beneficiall planete, (who for his ineſtimable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and vpright dealinge, were worthy of al honor, and to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt place in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> celeſtial ſcheme: But alas, like as vpright, plain, and true dealyng men, are nowe a dayes litle ſet by, and nothyng regarded in the worlde: Euen ſo
<pb facs="tcp:23740:3"/>alas, I ſay alas is Iupiter thruſt downe, and as it were forſaken, by the permiſſion of God for a tyme. I founde Iupiter I ſaye, placed in the loweſt part of al the fygure. And to increaſe alſo the more his infortune, he is as well now retrograde, as he was the laſt yeare, and occidentall of the ſonne. The beſt comfort he hath is, that the gentyll and frendly, lady Venus hath lent him a lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng for a ſpace, &amp; yet that is no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginnyng of May: for then he muſt go a maying for one moneth and more, vntyll he returne agayne the .vi. daye of Iune, whiche beyng ones retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, wyll then take hart of grace,
<pb facs="tcp:23740:3"/>and be bolde to continue &amp; walke in his frende Venus her houſe, vntyl it be the <hi>.22.</hi> of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber.</p>
               <p>Conſideryng alſo with my ſelf the preuention goinge before, in the v. daye o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Marche, the Moone beyng in the houſe of Mercury, beynge alſo ſaluted the next mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe after, with the quartyle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of fyery Mars, not to her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentation. The Sunne alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a quartyle aſpecte with Mars: I can not perceaue, but that muche myſery and trouble wyll happen in this Reuolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as nowe I wyll in particular more largely declare.</p>
               <p>Mars being in the aſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in
<pb facs="tcp:23740:4"/>a ſeptentrional ſigne portendeth a certayn earthquake to happen this yere, either in England, or els in ſome countrey nighe adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and ſpecially about the latter end of the ſommer: it wil cauſe al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo ſeldome rayne. I gather alſo, <hi>Ex <hi>tali eius ſitu,</hi>
                  </hi> that muche cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, extortion, vſury, contentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſuche lyke horrible vices, are lyke to reigne among men, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing therby many, to be very pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſife, and full of anguyſhe and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe. For many wil be ready to ſcratche out other mennes eyes, for to take &amp; rauiſh their goodes. And other that can not ſo viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhal aſſay by al craft and ſubtil policie, to conuey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23740:4"/>away into their handes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by gods plagues ar lyke to come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. Therfore O ye extortio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, O ye vnſatiable vſurers, al ye vnmerciful, gredy, &amp; couetous ryche men, take hede, take hede, repent, for it is more than hyghe tyme. <hi>Praeſto eſt dies Domini, dies irae O calamitatis, dies illa tremenda &amp; a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mara ualde. Dum dies eſt igitur &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pus habemus, operemur bonum, quia quando nox ue nit. i. poſt mortem, nemo poterit operari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The forſayd Mars placed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of Cancer, ſignifieth ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyn ſhipwrackes, by occaſion of great &amp; ſodein blaſtes of windes: alſo ſtrife, contention, and warre in the weſt partes: impoſitions
<pb facs="tcp:23740:5"/>of ſubſydies &amp; newe paymentes, dyuers diſeaſes: for Mars is lord of the vi. houſe, as hotte agues, pleureſies, ſquinances, inflama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, head ache, meigrym, peyn in the ſtomack, in the ſmal guts, in the back and ſydes, and vlce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matrice, priuy partes and fundment: alſo great heate, and litle rayne, no great ſtore of butter. Item, the death of cattel, and all other beaſtes, but chiefly of horſes: The water of welles to be very lowe, for lacke of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſprynges. And that the vulgar people and huſbandmen, ſhalbe dylygent and carefull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theyr own buſynes. They hadde nede ſo. I perceaue by the
<pb facs="tcp:23740:5"/>lorde of this reuolution, and the trine aſpect of the Sunne to the Moone, that marchantes and all other occupiers, and craftſmen, ſhal haue ſome better gaynes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were wonte to haue of late yeres, and that as well by lande as by ſea. Alſo wyſe and learned men, ſerthes, regiſters, ſecreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, aſtronomers, and chyldren, ſhall proſper better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were wont to doe: beſides that there is lyke to be muche ſtore of fyſhe.</p>
               <p>As concernyng warre, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue that Mars placed in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent, beynge alſo ſeptentrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall &amp; direct, hauyng no leſſe then fyue dignities in Cancer: hathe arm<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d hymſelfe from toppe to toe, ready to enter into the field,
<pb facs="tcp:23740:6"/>and wyl do what he can, to bring the people out of quiet: yet not withſtanding, they of Mercurius ſide (whom I take to be certayne wyſe and politike men, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, doctors, ſcribes, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes, &amp; other learned men,) wil ſo, I hope, ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle the matter that they ſhall ſcone repreſſe the ſtoute inuaſion and furious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe of Mars. For although he ſhould rage neuer ſo muche at the beginning: yea. May beynge ones entred, approchinge to the <hi>28.</hi> degree of Cancer: he ſhoulde haue for recompence, a foule ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefull fall.</p>
               <p>Iupiter being retrograde and occidentall, hauyng no aſpect w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23740:6"/>the lord of the reuolution, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſorowe, muche care &amp; feare to fall vpon the people. And alſo muche debate and ſtrife in the lawe, for matters concerning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, ſucceſſions, landes, goodes, and debtes, lefte by the dead. In whiche thynges not a fewe ſhall loaſe their righte, and ſhall not be able to proſecute the lawe.</p>
               <p>Mercurius placed in the .ix. houſe, ſheweth, that certayne wytty, politike, and learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with the helpe of the higher po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, ſhall go about to eſtabliſh matters in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet Iupiter being retrograde in the fourthe houſe, ſemeth to be an occaſion,
<pb facs="tcp:23740:7"/>that all thynges ſhall not ſo well goe forwarde, as the Mercuria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes woulde haue it. The ſame teſtifyeng alſo the wyly and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teryng trine aſpect of Mars vnto the ſayde Mercurie. To whome Mars is alwayes mortall enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye. Whyche thyng to be true, the very phyloſophers haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes teſtified, by this prouerbe <hi>Nihil Marti cum Muſis. Mercuriales autem prae caeteris muſarum cultores ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As touchyng Saturne, thys generall rule is alwayes to bee noted, (of the whiche ſomewhat I ſpake in my laſt yeares Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſlication) that as often as he is founde in a fire ſigne, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:23740:7"/>in Leo: he declareth morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, with penury of corn, graſſe, of dyuers fruites, ſedes, flowers herbes, and rootes.</p>
               <p>Alſo corruption of the ayre, groſſe myſtes, darke and cloudy wether, with ſome earthquake in the eaſt partes. And becauſe he is Septentrionall and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trograde, ſygnifyeth alſo greate ſhowres of rayne, corruption and deſtruction, as well of the great mennes goodes, as of the goodes of common people, and of marchantes: peſtilence, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yuers other long and greuous diſeaſes. Alſo diſſention &amp; muche ſtrife betwene brothers. <hi>Sol in x. conſtitutus, Reg<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ae honorem exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationem,
<pb facs="tcp:23740:8"/>eiuſque gloriam atque profectii ſignat.</hi> By the poſition of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, I fynd, that muche trouble diſſention and hatred, ſhall bee cauſed through certain women, and chiefly by thoſe that be of the baſer ſorte, and ſcarſly reputed honeſt. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in 6. domicilio caeli</hi> ſheweth the rancor and diſcorde of certain fathers, the gayne of graſiers and horſcorſers, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo health to the body, ſauing that Mars is lyke to haue the vpper hand in this poynt, as is ſayde afore. I perceiue that <hi>excapito daa conis in ſcorpione,</hi> the meaner ſorte of people, ſhall haue cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, by occaſion of ſome good luck that ſhal happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto them.
<pb facs="tcp:23740:8"/>But the lighter ſort are lyke to fele ſome trouble &amp; ſorow. Alſo is ſignified diſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, warre, wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, and much fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with deceit. And that al kynde of beaſtes (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be rydden ſhal much increace. Seruantes alſo ſhal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erece, I meane, that there ſhal be many many mo ſeruantes then was wont to be. God graunt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei be true &amp; good, I would mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney wold increaſe as well amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the poore commons. But of the increaſe I can finde nothyng by my calculatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Cauda draconis n.12. poſita,</hi> declareth ſom aduerſite, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greater kynd of beaſtes &amp; ſmal power to the enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hactenus de priori reuolutione.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13 September-12 March" type="astronomical_half-year">
               <pb facs="tcp:23740:9"/>
               <head>¶ Of the ſeconde part or reuolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conteinyng the other halfe of the Aſtronomical yere, which beginneth preciſely, the. <hi>13.</hi> day of September, at. <hi>8.</hi> of the clock at nyght.</head>
               <p>IN the celeſtiall figure of the ſeconde Reuolution, I fynde the begynnynge of Taurus to be aſcendent. In the whiche Venus is lady of the ſayd aſcendent. But Iupiter is the Lorde of the reuolution, geuyng ſome parte of hys dominion to Mercury.</p>
               <p>All the Planeites (beyng as they were agreed and of one mynde,</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:23740:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
